<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>NP Complete Heart (Posts about book)</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/categories/book.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:adamrpah@gmail.com"&gt;Adam Pah&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 15:22:29 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Follow me on the Reading Rainbow</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/follow-me-on-the-reading-rainbow/</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="row"&gt;
&lt;div class="col-md-4"&gt;
    &lt;img src="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/images/everything_is_obvious.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="col-md-8"&gt;
Over the summer I've been able to successfully chisel away at my goal of reading 20 books by 16
different authors in 2015, with my two weeks of travel to and around Spain providing me ample time
to dive into my iPad and digest. For this tour, I went back in time and read Nicholas Christakis'
&lt;strong&gt;Connected&lt;/strong&gt;, which actually provided me with some insight on researchers and topics that I thought I
already knew pretty well. In terms of an overview of how networks affect social phenomena, I would
highly recommend it. I also plowed through Nate Silver's &lt;strong&gt;The Signal and The Noise&lt;/strong&gt;, because I'm
convinced that being acquainted with Nate Silver's work is the litmus test in the public for
understanding data science. It was pretty good, although some of his metaphors were clunky and only
really stuck with me because of reading fivethirtyeight (his own data science news blog) since its
inception.
&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/follow-me-on-the-reading-rainbow/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (2 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>research</category><category>review</category><category>social influence</category><category>social science</category><category>socialdna</category><category>socialdna readings</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/follow-me-on-the-reading-rainbow/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 14:41:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How does cooperation evolve?</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/how-does-cooperation-evolve/</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="row"&gt;
&lt;div class="col-md-8"&gt;
I just finished reading Axelrod's &lt;strong&gt;The Complexity of Cooperation&lt;/strong&gt; and I have to say, it's one of the better scientific books that I can remember reading (period). This is surprising (for me), since it's really just a collection of seven of his published papers along with some commentary. However, his papers are so well written and the commentary is brilliant, especially for someone pursuing research as a career, since it not only provides insight into the genesis of the work but also how it was regarded by journals.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="col-md-4"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/images/prisoners_dilemma.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/how-does-cooperation-evolve/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (6 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>rationality</category><category>review</category><category>science</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/how-does-cooperation-evolve/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2015 14:47:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>2014 Literature Round up</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/2014-literature-round-up/</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="book review" src="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/images/2014_roundup_zpsff71df98.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Twenty fourteen, what can I say. It was consistent and not always pretty but I made it through. I made my first actual contribution to an &lt;a href="http://github.com/python-visualization/folium/commits?author=adamrpah"&gt;open source project&lt;/a&gt;, learned the value of gists, started opening up &lt;a href="http://github.com/adamrpah/GALE"&gt;GALE&lt;/a&gt; to the world, and successfully made it through putting on a one week bootcamp transform non-coders into pythonistas. I at least got one manuscript out (albeit a &lt;a href="http://npcompleteheart.com/article/big-data-what-is-it-and-what-does-it-mean-for-card/"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;) and a conference presentation at &lt;a href="http://npcompleteheart.com/article/unzipping-zip-codes-a-methodology-to-assign-de-ide/"&gt;AMIA&lt;/a&gt;. I even launched Socraticc as a part of OmegaK and brought it right down after no one wanted to use it after a few months.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/2014-literature-round-up/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>review</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/2014-literature-round-up/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 14:43:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A story of human reasoning</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/a-story-of-human-reasoning/</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h5&gt;(a first part summary of essays contained within Gigerenzer and Selten's [eds.] &lt;i&gt;Bounded Rationality: The Adaptive Toolbox&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What will I make for dinner? A relatively simple question that plagues me most nights of the week. However, what is a relatively simple task, albeit one that can be arduous for me, unpacks a can of worms in basic research: through what &lt;b&gt;mental process&lt;/b&gt; do I decide what to make?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Admittedly this is a silly question, but other questions used to motivate this issue are roughly as silly. The point is merely to illuminate the difference between decision-making paradigms. Classically, or as far as my knowledge extends to, we would typically think of solving this problem through maximizing our utility, searching for the best possible answer (the global optima). In the context of our dinner problem, the steps to solving our problem would look like:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mentally assemble all of the possible recipes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;determine which recipes had all of the possible recipes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;determine which recipes had all available ingredients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;account for the spoilage dates of all the ingredients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify the meal that would provide the maximum utility (one that uses the most ingredients that are about to spoil the soonest while being feasible to make)&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/a-story-of-human-reasoning/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>rationality</category><category>review</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/a-story-of-human-reasoning/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 14:41:27 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>