<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NP Complete Heart (conference)</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" href="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/categories/conference.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 02:00:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Computational research, no longer a red-headed stepchild!</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/computational-research-no-longer-a-red-headed-stepchild.html</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="row"&gt;
&lt;div class="col-md-8"&gt;
Research Day as a chairperson and poster judge.I typically cringe at the thought of attending
conferences and symposia, since I am mainly a homebody (I love my desk, computer, research, and
daily schedule), but at the symposium on Tuesday I felt constantly excited and engaged. The variety
and quality of research presented was excellent and the diverse topics covered kept the gears
turning in my head.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="col-md-4"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/images/computational_research_day.jpg" height="150px"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;

&lt;div class="col-md-12"&gt;
Most importantly, the sense of camaraderie that I felt amongst these computational researchers kept
me energized. I wish that this event existed when I started graduate school. As a computational
researcher that was purportedly a biologist, it was easy to feel that I was a part of a group that I
was a red-headed stepchild. My home program was primarily concerned with experimentation or the
application of rote computational biology (i.e. anything involving a computer that would have been
published since the early 90s). Most of the other departments that included some computational
research were ones where computational methods were de rigeur and field specific research dominated.
Instead I was looking more for what made me gravitate towards the Northwestern Institute for
complexity, computational researchers that were applying new techniques and conducting
interdisciplinary research.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
I can’t wait to see what new problems people will tackle as the quantity, diversity, and
interdisciplinarity of computational research continues to expand. Because of my experience in
biology, I realize how important it is to bring other fields and researcher into the fold of the
computational community. It will help change how people view their research problems and hopefully
lead to better research. This is what drives me to help put on the bootcamps as an introduction to
programming and data science. It’s also why I believe that events like the Computational Research
Day are integral to a healthy, productive research environment at a University.
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Keep Growing, Computational Research! Keep Growing!
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>conference</category><category>research</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/computational-research-no-longer-a-red-headed-stepchild.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:56:52 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>