<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>NP Complete Heart (random)</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" href="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/categories/random.xml" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 03:07:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>I made a Wordpress site on Heroku!</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/i-made-a-wordpress-site-on-heroku.html</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="row"&gt;
&lt;div class="col-md-8"&gt;
Well, not for me of course. After a solid week of my girlfriend helping me to use Illustrator it was
time to pay her back and help her get a website up and running. I went over the options that I knew
(Nikola, Django, Node.js, Ruby on Rails) and it became quickly apparent that none of those were
options that she liked. Instead she wanted to take a wordpress site that she made in a class and add
some more to it/fix it up. The only logistical issue is that it's hard to find a wordpress host for
free that allows you to use a custom domain (she's about to graduate from school so it's important
that she have a real website name). For that privilege wordpress.org charges you $8/mon, which,
while I may know nothing about Wordpress, I find to be crazy.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="col-md-4"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/images/wordpress_heroku.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;div class="col-md-12"&gt;
So instead I went around searching for how to shoehorn Wordpress onto Heroku's Cedar stack (which is
where Django ends up). Luckily others have already had this desire and it was super easy!  Using
this &lt;a src="https://github.com/mhoofman/wordpress-heroku"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; repository and README I had the
wordpress site up and running in seconds. Woot!
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>code</category><category>random</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/i-made-a-wordpress-site-on-heroku.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 14:41:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sometimes things are strange</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/sometimes-things-are-strange.html</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="strange" src="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/images/sometimes_things_are_strange.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offered without comment, in this the year 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>artesque</category><category>random</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/sometimes-things-are-strange.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 14:36:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Arthur the overly adult half breed aardvark</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/arthur-the-overly-adult-half-breed-aardvark.html</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Arthur!" src="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/images/aardvark.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>artesque</category><category>random</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/arthur-the-overly-adult-half-breed-aardvark.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 12:58:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Man, I wish inspiration could strike me so I could just name this website</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/man-i-wish-inspiration-could-strike-me-so-i-could-just-name-this-website.html</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I've been working with my friend for awhile now and for the entire length of our project we've struggled to name it.
Over the last week we finally bit the bullet and decided that we would finally name it so other people could start using it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was a struggle. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We weren't really sure what idea or concept we wanted the name to embody so I wrote this script up to try and help.
Given a list of seed words from the command line it gets a number of similar words using the word net corpus.
Then it goes through those words to see if any have an ending that is the same as a generic top level domain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
'''
File: naming_domains.py
Author: Adam Pah
Description: 
Script to help in naming/brainstorming web domains
Recursively grabs a number of words that are synonyms to a starting
list of words. Then checks the ends of the words to see if they match 
any of a number of common web TLDs. 
'''

#Standard path imports
from optparse import OptionParser
import re

#Non-standard imports
from nltk.corpus import wordnet
import whois

#Global directories and variables
end_list = ['org', 'com', 'net', 'mobi', 'es', 'us', 'es', 'cc', 'mobi', 'co', 'info', 'ca', 'biz', 'me', 'tv', 'ws', 'asia', 'la']

def regexify_endings(end_list):
    '''
    Takes the list of possible TLD endings and constructs a dictionary
    that matches up the 'end' to the regex
    '''
    ends = {}
    for x in end_list:
        ends[x] = re.compile(x + '$')
    return ends

def identify_additional_words(seed, max_list_size, word_list = []):
    '''
    Identifies addtional words/synonyms given a starting list of words.
    Keeping track of loop iterations to give a break condition too, in case
    the seed words are so small/narrow that it just loops on itself.
    '''
    num_try = 1
    while len(word_list)  1000:
        for seed_word in seed:
            for lemma_start in wordnet.synsets(seed_word):
                for lemma_word in lemma_start.lemma_names:
                    word_list.append(lemma_word)
        word_list = list(set(word_list))
        disjoint = set(word_list).difference(set(seed))
        seed = list(disjoint)
        num_try += 1
    return word_list

def identify_matched_endings(endings, word_list):
    '''
    Searches through the word list for ones that have an end that matches
    a possilbe TLD.
    '''
    for word in word_list:
        for end_name, endr in endings.items():
            if endr.findall(word) != []:
                print "%s -- %s" % (word, end_name)

if __name__ == '__main__':
    usage = '%prog [options]'
    parser = OptionParser(usage = usage)
    parser.add_option('-n', '--num', action='store', default=100,
                      help='Number of words to return/find')
    (opt, args) = parser.parse_args()
    #####
    endings = regexify_endings(end_list)
    if args:
        word_list = identify_additional_words(args, opt.num)
        identify_matched_endings(endings, word_list)
    else:
        print '''ERROR: Must have starting set of words\n
                 Please enter command line list of seed words'''
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>python</category><category>random</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/man-i-wish-inspiration-could-strike-me-so-i-could-just-name-this-website.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2014 12:47:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Is it Easter time yet?</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/is-it-easter-time-yet.html</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I'm developing an node.js application with a friend and after a few weeks of actual coding we decided to change the name of one of the models from "Organization" to "Board". Pretty simple change actually, the design of the app had changed slightly enough that the rewording would make more mental sense for us.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So as I'm on the call I change the initial model details in the file and then change it in the router file where I know it's been used so far. Before I add the changes and commit though, I just run a quick check to make sure that it doesn't appear anywhere else like so:
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;
$ grep -R organization .
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
...and then I got this fun little surprise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
lola:company-dumps adampah$ grep -r organization .
./node_modules/handlebars/node_modules/optimist/node_modules/wordwrap/test/idleness.txt:Modern technique has made it possible to diminish enormously the amount of labor required to secure the necessaries of life for everyone. This was made obvious during the war. At that time all the men in the armed forces, and all the men and women engaged in the production of munitions, all the men and women engaged in spying, war propaganda, or Government offices connected with the war, were withdrawn from productive occupations. In spite of this, the general level of well-being among unskilled wage-earners on the side of the Allies was higher than before or since. The significance of this fact was concealed by finance: borrowing made it appear as if the future was nourishing the present. But that, of course, would have been impossible; a man cannot eat a loaf of bread that does not yet exist. The war showed conclusively that, by the scientific organization of production, it is possible to keep modern populations in fair comfort on a small part of the working capacity of the modern world. If, at the end of the war, the scientific organization, which had been created in order to liberate men for fighting and munition work, had been preserved, and the hours of the week had been cut down to four, all would have been well. Instead of that the old chaos was restored, those whose work was demanded were made to work long hours, and the rest were left to starve as unemployed. Why? Because work is a duty, and a man should not receive wages in proportion to what he has produced, but in proportion to his virtue as exemplified by his industry.
./node_modules/handlebars/node_modules/optimist/node_modules/wordwrap/test/idleness.txt:If the ordinary wage-earner worked four hours a day, there would be enough for everybody and no unemployment -- assuming a certain very moderate amount of sensible organization. This idea shocks the well-to-do, because they are convinced that the poor would not know how to use so much leisure. In America men often work long hours even when they are well off; such men, naturally, are indignant at the idea of leisure for wage-earners, except as the grim punishment of unemployment; in fact, they dislike leisure even for their sons. Oddly enough, while they wish their sons to work so hard as to have no time to be civilized, they do not mind their wives and daughters having no work at all. the snobbish admiration of uselessness, which, in an aristocratic society, extends to both sexes, is, under a plutocracy, confined to women; this, however, does not make it any more in agreement with common sense.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I love it. :)
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>artesque</category><category>random</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/is-it-easter-time-yet.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2013 12:44:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What to do with 1,000 business cards?</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/what-to-do-with-1000-business-cards.html</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dumb business cards" src="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/images/ttx_phone.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, at least they make great structural support.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cheeky</category><category>random</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/what-to-do-with-1000-business-cards.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 12:43:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>You know what, I'm going to stand by it.</title><link>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/you-know-what-im-going-to-stand-by-it.html</link><dc:creator>Adam Pah</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SQL Sucks" src="http://www.npcompleteheart.com/images/sql_twitter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>random</category><category>soapbox</category><guid>http://www.npcompleteheart.com/posts/you-know-what-im-going-to-stand-by-it.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2013 12:42:27 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>